<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to a foreigner, on the present debates about a standing army</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48154</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11346</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12387116</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12387116</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60880</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48154)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60880)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 766:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to a foreigner, on the present debates about a standing army</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Dan Brown ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army.</term>
               <term>Standing army.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60880:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
            <p>A LETTER TO A FOREIGNER, ON THE Preſent Debates About a <hi>Standing Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Nec ſumit aut ponit ſecures</l>
               <l>Arbitrio popularis aurae.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Dan Brown,</hi> at the Black-Swan and Bible without <hi>Temple-bar,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:60880:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60880:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
            <head>A LETTER TO A FOREIGNER, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU that are of no Party, and have no Stake to hazard, are in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereſt light to determine the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of others; and the Alliance of your Country may give you a juſt Title to intereſt your ſelf in the Concerns of ours.</p>
            <p>You are not to be told, that the end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one War, has been the occaſion of another; which may prove more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, as it is more near; and that the Pen is become more formidable than the Sword.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:60880:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <p>But are you not a little ſurpriz'd to ſee Men quarrel with ſo much obſtinacy, and foment ſuch deſtructive Heats; when if the Matter were truly conſider'd, they might be found, perhaps, to mean the ſame thing? And when we have no ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled Notion of what we talk, our Diſputes will be Eternal.</p>
            <p>You very judiciouſly obſerve, that hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto the Arguments of either ſide, like <hi>Cadmus</hi>'s Souldiers, have defeated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: for one is abhorring the Thoughts of a <hi>Standing Army,</hi> while he is preparing you to continue it from Year to Year; the other tells you, that no Peace is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, that has occaſion for ſo much as the Uſe or Exerciſe of Arms, and at the ſame time lays you down a Model of Diſcipline for a <hi>Militia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not enter into a Debate, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the former or the latter be moſt in the wrong, but will reduce the whole Matter to this one Queſtion, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Whether our Freedom and our nation be more ſafe under the Army, (for ſo I ſhall diſtinguiſh 'em in the following part of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60880:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->my Letter) or the Militia, which I take to be the ſum of all our Differences?</p>
            <p>But before I offer at that Deciſion, I will firſt obviate this preliminary Difficulty, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Now we have a Peace, we are to turn our Swords into Plowſhares, and our Spears into Pruning-hooks, and believe that it cannot conſiſt with the Freedom of any State to ſtudy the uſe of Arms, or make War their Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>To anſwer this I will only ſay, That the greateſt States of the World have ow'd their Freedom to their Arms, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported it by nothing elſe. The <hi>Romans</hi> are chiefly inſtanc'd to prove the contrary; now if what the <hi>Romans</hi> did will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd, that part of the Diſpute will end.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romans</hi> you know from an infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous handful of Slaves and Runnagates, became the glorious Lords of the World, and acquired by their Arms a freedom of their City, that all Nations coveted, tho few were honour'd with: theſe People from the founding of their City, to the Diſſolution of their Empire, were in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual War; the Exerciſe and Neceſſity of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60880:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->Arms was ſo interwoven in their Life, that it may be juſtly call'd a <hi>Martial Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and one continually increaſing Army, that at laſt ſpread it ſelf over the whole World. Will any one believe if it had not been for a Profeſſion of Arms, and a Genius to War, that they would ever have flouriſh'd their Colours of Hay over ſo many Nations?</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Sir,</hi> to make you better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of our Debate, it will not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable to repreſent to you the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of our Army and our Militia.</p>
            <p>There is ſomething in the braveſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that will not ſecure it ſelf againſt Surprizes; 'tis therefore neceſſary in a Souldier to know the face of an Enemy, to feel the hardſhips of a Camp, and grow familiar with Dangers —,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Vitam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſub dio, &amp; trepidis agat</l>
               <l>In rebus —.</l>
            </q>
            <p>How much this is the Qualification of our Army, and how far they have differenc'd themſelves from other Nations, you are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60880:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->not to be told; but notwithſtanding you have ever expreſt a very diſtinguiſhing ſenſe of the Bravery of our Army, yet compar'd to the Courage and Fortitude of our Militia, it is nothing! our Militia Souldier, without the Provocation of an Enemy, is call'd out of his Bed to Arms; he puts on his Armour of Buff that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Bullet yet enter'd; his Bandaleers he fills with Gunpowder, and his Pockets with Beef; thus dreſt for the War, and fearleſs of Dangers, in ſpite of Rain or Cold, his tender Wife and Children hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at his Sleeve, and tho he knows the Perils he's to meet,</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Non aliter tamen</l>
               <l>Dimovit obſtantes propinquos.</l>
            </q>
            <p>After the Fatigue of a whole Day, the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> returns with certain Triumph, ſettles himſelf in his arm'd Chair, and to his liſtening Progeny relates the Glories of the Field,
<q>
                  <l>—Geret<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>Praelia Conjugibus loquenda!</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60880:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->Now, <hi>Sir,</hi> were the Diſpute confin'd to the ſtrongeſt, the Matter, I fancy, might eaſily be determin'd; but it depends more upon a diffidence of our Army: and 'tis objected, That the General of ſuch a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy may enſlave his Country, and make himſelf a Tyrant when he pleaſes: they would remove this Army, and for their Security, would ſubſtitute a Train'd Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia, who will not act to the diſadvantage of the Conſtitution, unleſs we could ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to be <hi>Felons de ſe.</hi> This, <hi>Sir,</hi> is the inſuperable Bar; on this depends the whole Matter.</p>
            <p>It may be ſomething towards an Anſwer, to ſhow you how very difficult, if not impoſſible, it would be to form ours into a Trained Militia.</p>
            <p>Our Militia conſiſts of ſuch a number of Men, not the ſame Souldiers; for the Trading People that compoſe the greater part, ſeldom have the leiſure, or think it worth their while to neglect their Buſineſs to trail a Pike, or diſcharge a Musket, but hire others (not always the ſame) whoſe Courage they can depend on to ſuſtain the Service.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60880:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
            <p>But to place the Argument in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Extremity; ſuppoſing theſe Men of Property were oblig'd to fight their own Battels, and were continually exercis'd, the Power muſt ſtill reſt in one Man, who according to their own Arguments, may make himſelf a Tyrant when he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>But 'tis to be depended on, that the Souldiers would refuſe to obey in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Deſign againſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs that Model of an Army is very extraordinary, where the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Right and Wrong muſt reſide in the Tumult! And if our Security is to ariſe only from a hope of their Refuſal, I would fain ask any ſober Man, if our boaſted Freedom will not ſtand upon a very tickliſh Point? and who would ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that the Modellers of an Army ſhould lay down Diſobedience as a material part of their Diſcipline?</p>
            <p>Now from Examples of all Armies that have been yet known, it is inconſiſtent with the Notion of a General not to be Arbitrary; ſo that whatever the People be, the Power is ſtill the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:60880:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
            <p>Were I directing my ſelf to any but you, <hi>Sir,</hi> I ſhould a little inlarge on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; but I don't queſtion, after what you have heard already, but this will be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to give you a true Idea of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Differences.</p>
            <p>I will add this Obſervation more, That from what has been ſaid on all hands, it is evident there muſt be ſome Truſt; and I would fain know if there is any People in the World but may be enſlav'd by their own Government? The Truſt you make, place it where you will, may be us'd to your Deſtruction. And ſince it appears that our Danger is the ſame from a <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> as an <hi>Army,</hi> what will be the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of ſo great an Innovation? This very Liberty of which we are ſo jealous, is owing to our Army; and could you imagine that we who are the only Gainers, ſhould make that an Argument to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their Livings, for which they have hazarded their Lives?</p>
            <p>I have heard of a Creature that cannot be born without the Death of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but as Life is a leſſer Boon than
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60880:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->Liberty, Man muſt be the greater Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to whom the Memory of good Offices is ſo odious.</p>
            <p>'Tis our Character not to know our own Happineſs, and a ſudden Peace has tranſported us too much: Eaſe and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence are the difficult Sea of Humane Life; in Adverſity we are ſomewhat guided by the Neceſſity of it, but here the Pilot is in danger, and he muſt be a judicious Mariner that is not loſt in this Storm,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ab inſolenti temperatam</l>
               <l>Laetitia.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>I am pleas'd to think that (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ungrateful Diffidence and infamous Murmurings of ſome Spirits among us, againſt the Man that triumphs o're their Enemies) he rules with an innate Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without provocation by our good or bad Actions, and will, I hope, in ſpite of all the Inſinuations of ill Men, flouriſh unſhaken by their Malice, or what is yet more treacherous, their Praiſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
